*34C3 preroll music*
34C3 Ultimate Talk
Michael SteilChristian Hessmann
Herald: The following talk is about a very relevant piece of technological legacy of our human race.
The first piece of computer that landed on our moon and actually it became a metric.
People started to compare other architectures, other computers
in volumes of multiples of processing speed of this computer.
It's rocket science, but it's even harder: it's computer rocket science.
So I'm very happy to have Christian Hessmann, or Hessie, on stage who is actually a rocket scientist.
Christian Hessmann
And for the ... *laughter* ... for the computer part we have Michael Steil
Michael Steil
who is the founder of the Xbox Linux project and has gathered with this project and many others
Xbox Linux
lots and lots of experience around architectures of computers.
So please give a warm round of applause for the Ultimate Apollo Guidance talk!
*applause*
Michael Steil: Welcome! Is this on? Can you all hear me? Yes.
Michael Steil
Welcome to the Ultimate Apollo Guidance Computer Talk,
a.k.a. a comprehensive introduction into computer architecture.
And operating systems.
And spaceflight. *laughter*
My name is Michael Steil ...
Michael Steil
Christian: ... and I'm Christian Hessmann.
Christian Hessmann
Michael: This talk is number six in a series by various people.
The idea is to explain as much as possible about a classic computer system in 60 minutes.
The Apollo Guidance Computer AGC is a digital computer that was designed from scratch
AGC
specifically for use on board of the Apollo spacecraft
to support the Apollo moon landings between 1969 and 1972.
19691972
Developed at MIT between 1961 and 1966
MIT19611966
a total of 42 AGCs were built at a cost of about $200,000 each.
42AGC$200,000
The base clock is about one megahertz, all data is 15 bits,
1MHz15
and there are two kilowords of RAM and 36 kiloword ROM, words of ROM.
2KiRAM36KiROM
It's about the size of a large suitcase, weighs 32 kilograms and consumes about 55 watts.
Its user interface is a numeric display and keyboard.
Some historical context: In the mid 1960s you couldn't just take
an off-the-shelf computer and put it into a spacecraft.
The first mini computers were the size of a small fridge -
too heavy, to power-hungry and too slow for real-time scientific calculations,
even though the industry had come a long way since the previous decade.
Already 10 years later though, microcomputers with highly integrated circuits
started outclassing the AGC Hardware in many regards.
AGC
There are many reasons that make the AGC especially interesting:
The architecture is very 60s and feels very alien to us today,
the hardware is very innovative for its time.
It has some very interesting and unusual peripherals.
Its operating system was revolutionary for its time and
the mission software has all the bits to - with the right hardware attached -
fly you to the moon.
C: In the Apollo program,
the Apollo guidance computer was used in two unmanned test missions,
where it was remote control from the ground,
and three manned test missions, and in the seven manned landing missions.
Astronauts hated the idea of giving up any control to a computer,
they wanted to be in charge.
And while as a fallback, most of the mission could also be flown manually,
the mission planners got their way.
To understand the purpose and the responsibilities of the Apollo Guidance Computer,
we need to first look at the Apollo mission.
The core strategy of the Apollo program was,
instead of landing the complete spacecraft on the moon,
for which an extremely large rocket would have been required,
to only land a much smaller lander
while the larger part with the fuel for the way back stays in orbit.
So the Apollo spacecraft can be separated into the lunar module,
the command module and the service module.
The Saturn 5 rocket launches it and three astronauts from Cape Kennedy into Earth orbit.
By accelerating at the right time the translunar injection moves the spacecraft
into a so-called free return orbit,
but just coasting it would travel around the moon and back to earth.
Right at the beginning of this three-day journey
the command and service module extracts the lunar module and docks with it.
By braking on the far side of the moon the spacecraft enters a lunar orbit.
After two of the astronauts have climbed into the lunar module,
and after undocking, the lunar module breaks -
this is called powered descent -
and lands.
*Applause*
After taking off again, the lunar module rendezvous with the command and service module
and the two astronauts from the lunar module climb into the command module
and the lunar module is jettisoned.
The remaining command and service module accelerates at the far side of the Moon
for trajectory towards Earth.
For entry, only the command module remains.
By the way, these excellent visualizations
are from Jared Owen's "How the Apollo spacecraft works" videos,
Jared OwenHow the Apollo spacecraft works
which we can highly recommend.
The command and service module and the lunar module each contained one a AGC.
AGC
It was the same hardware, but attached to partially different I/O devices,
IO
and with the software adapted for the specific spacecraft.
The astronauts interact with them through the display and keyboard units,
which are mounted alongside these hundreds of switches.
The computer's responsibilities during the mission are to track the position and speed,
the so called state vector of both spacecraft,
stabilize the spacecraft's attitude, calculate the control engine burns
and monitor or control the Saturn V during launch.
M: In order to understand how the Apollo guidance computer does all this,
we'll look at its architecture, the hardware implementation,
some of its interesting peripherals, the system software
as well as ... the system software as well as the mission software.
The architecture of the AGC can be described as a Von Neumann accumulator machine
AGC
with 15 bit one's complement big-endian arithmetic.
So we'll talk about the instruction set,
the arithmetic model and instruction encoding as well as the memory model,
I/O operations and counters, and finally the interrupt model.
I/O
Machine code instruction sets vary widely.
The instruction set of a modern ARM processor,
ARM
which is mainly optimized for runtime performance consists of about 400 instructions.
Subleq is a language mostly of academic interest,
that shows that a single instruction
SUBLEQ
can be enough to solve the same problems as all other turing-complete languages.
While a more complex constructions, that can achieve higher code density
and contribute to higher performance,
it also generally means that the CPU will be drastically more complex.
CPU
A computer from the early 1960s consisted of only a few thousand transistors
as opposed to today's billions,
which is why this is the sweet spot for the AGC.
AGC36
36 instructions provided just about the performance that was required for the mission.
These are the 36 instructions: some load and store instructions,
36load/store
arithmetic and logic, control flow instructions,
I/O instructions and instructions for dealing with interrupts.
I/O
The memory model is the cornerstone of the instruction set.
Memory consists of 4096 cells, numbered in hexadecimal 000 through FFF.
4096000FFF
Each cell contains a 15 bit word, numbered between 0 and 7FFF.
1507FFF
Almost all changes in data - in memory go through a 15 bit accumulator,
I also called it A register.
A
A program can copy words between the accumulator and a memory cell,
but also add, subtract, multiply and divide values, as they are moved around.
The data in memory can have many meanings, depending on how it is interpreted.
These values may represent integers,
while those three words are meant to be decoded as machine code instructions.
Code and data in a single address space make the AGC a so-called Von Neumann machine.
AGC
The CPU's program counter PC always holds the address of the instruction to be executed next.
CPUPC
The 'load' instruction copies the contents of a given memory cell into the accumulator.
load
The PC goes on to the next instruction.
PC
The 'add' instruction adds contents of a given memory cell to the accumulator,
add
and the 'store' instruction copies the value in the accumulator into memory at a given location.
store
The generalized version of these instructions we just saw,
K
use K as a placeholder for a memory address as an argument.
These are cards that are quick reference of instructions.
This is the generic syntax of the instruction,
a short description, the exact operations in pseudocode -
this one takes a memory address k and adds it to a, the accumulator -
KA
the encoding of the instruction in memory, and the number of clock cycles.
The original syntax is the name the original designers gave to the instruction.
For this talk I have chosen a more modern syntax, here on the right,
which makes it much more easier, much easier to describe the CPU
both to people with and without a background in machine programming.
AGC
Let's have a look at the instruction set in detail.
Here's an example of the load instruction.
load
Load a comma indirect two zero zero.
load a 200
On the left you see the set of registers of the AGC.
AGC
Most operations work with the accumulator,
so we will be ignoring the other registers for now.
While executing this instruction, the CPU looks at memory at location two zero zero,
CPU200
reads its contents and copies it into the accumulator.
This is the store instruction "store", a load indirect two zero zero comma A.
store
load 200a
Like with all instructions the first argument is the destination - memory -
the second one the source - the accumulator.
It looks up address two zero zero in memory
CPU200
and copies the contents of the accumulator to that cell.
There's also an exchange instruction which can atomically swap
the contents of the accumulator and a memory cell.
The 'add' instruction will look up the contents of a given memory address
add
and add it to the contents of the accumulator
and store the result back into the accumulator.
And there's a 'subtract' instruction.
It takes the contents of memory address
and subtracts it from the content of the accumulator
and stores the result back into the accumulator.
The result of every subtraction can be negative,
so we need to talk about how negative numbers are expressed on the AGC.
AGC
Let's look at just 4 bit numbers.
4-bit unsigned integers can express values from 0 to 15
with sign and value encoding the uppermost bit corresponds to the sign,
and the remaining 3 bits represent the absolute value.
Consequently, there are separate values for plus 0 and minus 0.
+0-0
This encoding is hard to work with, since the 0 transitions need to be special cased.
One's Complement encoding has the order of the negative numbers reversed.
The 0 transitions are simpler now, but there's still two representations of 0.
+0-0
Modern Two's Complement encoding only has a single encoding for 0,
and it's fully backwards compatible with unsigned addition and subtraction.
In the 1960s, computers designed for scientific calculations are usually One's Complement
and so is the AGC.
AGC
Unsigned four bit numbers can express values from 0 to 15.
In One's Complement the values 0 through 7
match the unsigned values 0 through 7,
and the negative size side is organized like this:
Unlike Two's Complement, the two sides are perfectly symmetrical,
so negating a number is as easy as complementing it,
that is, flipping all the bits.
So the two representations of 0 are plus 0, with all 0 bits,
0+0
and minus 0, with all 1 bits.
1-0
Addition in the positive space is equivalent to the unsigned version,
same in the negative space when
mapping signed negative numbers to their unsigned counterparts.
It gets interesting when we have a 0 transition.
Signed 6 - 4 is 6 + (-4) which is unsigned 6 + 11,
6-46+46+11
which in modulus 16 is 1. We have a carry.
In One's Complement, a carry needs to be added to the end result,
so we get two, which is correct.
The trick to jump over the duplicate 0 on a zero-transition by adding the carries
is called the 'end-around-carry'.
An overflow means that the signed result does not fit into the number space.
Signed 7 + 1 would result in signed -7, which is incorrect.
47+1-7
The same happens when overshooting negative numbers.
After applying the end-around carry, the result of signed 7 here is incorrect.
-7-18+147
The CPU detects this and flags the result,
CPU
the accumulator has an extra bit to record
V
the information about an overflow, we call it V.
So if we have code that reads the value of 7FFF from memory
7FFF
and adds 1, the result is 0 and an overflow is detected,
A10CPU
so the accumulator is flagged.
V
The store instruction in addition to writing A to memory,
does extra work if there's an overflow condition:
store
it clears the overflow condition, writes plus 1 or minus 1 into A,
depending on whether it's a positive or a negative overflow,
A+1-1
and skips the next instruction.
This way the program can detect the overflow
and use the plus 1 or minus 1 to apply the signed carry to a higher-order word.
A+1-1/
By storing A to memory, we now have a double-word result.
A
In one's complement negating a number is as easy as flipping every bit in a word
so there's a dedicated instruction for loading and negating a value.
ldc, which stands for 'load complement', reads a word from memory,
ldc
negates it by inverting all the bits and writes it into the accumulator.
Incrementing, that is adding 1 to a word, is such a common operation
that there's a dedicated instruction that increments a word in memory in place.
AGC1
There is no corresponding decrement instruction.
Instead, there are two similar instructions: augment and diminish.
The increment instruction adds one to the original value,
the augment instruction adds one to all positive values
and subtracts 1 from all negative values.
Effectively increments the absolute value retaining the sign.
The diminish instruction decrements positive values and increments negative values.
Optimized for scientific calculations, the CPU has dedicated multiplication circuitry.
CPU
The model instruction reads a word from memory and multiplies it with the accumulator.
mul
When you multiply two signed 15 bit words,
you need up to 29 bits, that is two words, for the result.
The complete result will be written into two registers,
the upper half into A and the lower half into B.
AB
B is a separate 15 bit register which is mostly used together with the accumulator
B15
with instructions that deal with 30 bit data.
Double word values are expressed with the uppermost bits in A,
A
or, if in memory, at lower addresses,
and the lower bits in B, or at higher addresses,
B
making the AGC a big endian machine.
AGC
Assuming the normalized form, with matching signs,
AB
the effective value is the concatenation of the two times 14 bits of the values.
2x14
Division also works with double words.
It takes the combination of the A and B registers as the dividend
AB
and a word from memory as the divisor.
There are also two results: the result and the remainder.
The result is written into A and the remainder in to B.
AB
Some other instructions also allow using A and B as a double word register.
Load a b comma indirect two zero zero looks up addresse two zero zero in memory
load ab 200200
and reads the words at this and the next cell into A and B.
AB
The load complement variant does the same but inverts all bits during the load.
There is no instruction to store A and B in a single step,
ABstore
but there is a double word exchange instruction.
And finally there's an add instruction that works in double words.
And to load and store just the B register there's an exchange instruction for that.
B
For working with tables there's the indexed addressing mode.
Any instruction that takes an address as an argument can use it.
This example 'load A comma indirect 7 0 0 plus indirect 8 0'
load a70080
first looks up address 0 8 0, adds it to the base of 7 0 0, which results in 7 0 2,
080700702
reads from that address and writes the result into A.
A
What does this mean? There's a table in memory at 7 0 0.
In the example, it contains multiples of 3,
and an index to that table is stored in memory at 0 8 0, which in the example is 2.
So we read the entry at index 2 of the table, which is 6.
Without a base address, we get the syntax in this example:
load A comma double indirect 8 0.
load a 80
The base is effectively zero in this case.
The CPU will look up the value at 0 8 0 in memory, add it to the base of 0,
CPU0800
so the value is still the same. And read from that address.
In this case, memory at 0 8 0 effectively stores what C programmers know as a pointer,
080C
and 3A0 is the pointer's different destination.
3A0
The instruction performed it indirectly.
By default, instructions are executed sequentially.
The program counter PC increments as instructions are executed,
PC
always pointing to the next instruction.
Control flow instructions like jump and conditional jump change that.
/
When the CPU hits a jump instruction, it will load its argument into the program counter,
CPUPC
which means that execution will continue at that address.
CPU
jz, jump if zero, only jumps if A is zero. Otherwise it continues with the next instruction.
jz0A0
Similarly, jlez only jumps if A is negative or zero.
jlezA0
CCS count compare and skip, is a fun one. It's a four-way fork for execution.
CCS4
Depending on whether the value in memory is positive, negative,
plus minus - plus zero, minus zero, it will jump to one of the next four instructions.
A+0-0
If you know the value is positive or zero,
A0
you can ignore the other two cases and just fill the first two slots.
And if it's supposed to be only negative, you have to skip the first two slots.
They should never be reached,
CPU
but it's good practice for them to fill them with error handlers.
Since CCS also puts the absolute diminished value of the memory location into A,
CCS1A
so it decrements A, a special case of CCS A
A
can be used for loops that count down A.
CCS
The call instruction. Isn't it for calling subroutines aka functions.
call
It's like a jump instruction but it saves its origin,
so the callee can return to it later.
For the call instruction, the program counter is incremented first,
callPC1LR
and then copied into the link register LR.
Finally, the argument of the call instruction is copied into the program counter,
callPC
so that execution continues there.
The link register now contains the return address.
LR
At the end of the subroutine,
the RET instruction effectively copies the contents of the linked register into the program counter,
retLRPC
so execution resumes just after the call instruction.
call
If the subroutine wants to call its own subroutine,
the program has to save the link register before,
LR
and restore it afterwards. There's an exchange instruction specifically for this.
LRLR
For additional levels, a stack can be constructed, manually, using the indexing syntax.
So far we've seen the following registers:
the A register is used for memory accesses and all arithmetic.
A
It is combined with the B register for double width arithmetic,
B
the program counter to keep track of what to execute
and the link register remembers the return address when calling a subroutine.
We haven't seen the zero register yet.
It always contains zero, so when we read from it, we get zero
and when we write to it the value gets discarded.
There are three more registers that we will talk about later.
The eight registers are numbered, that is they are assigned memory addresses.
This means that the first eight words in memory are actually occupied by the registers.
They can be accessed using the addresses and all instructions that take a memory address.
This allows for much greater flexibility in the instruction set:
we can load A with the contents of the B register
1A
by reading the contents of memory at location 1 into A.
BA
The content of zero can be loaded into A by just reading from memory at 7,
which is the zero register.
A can be incremented by incrementing memory at zero
0A
and B can be used as a pointer by reading from double indirect one.
1B
Let's look at memory more closely.
Memory is 4096 words and goes from 000 to FFF.
4096000FFF
The registers are located at the very bottom of memory.
Including them, there are 1024 words of RAM, random access memory,
1024RAM
and three kilowords of ROM, read-only memory.
3KiROM
The AGC was originally architected to only have this little RAM and ROM,
AGCRAMROM
but there's actually more. Let's look at the RAM area.
RAM
The uppermost quarter is banked.
RAM1/4bank
The area is a window through which one of eight different banks can be accessed,
8bank
each 250 words in size.
bank256
The erasable Bank register EB points to one of these banks.
bankEB
If EB is 0, Bank 0 is visible in the banked area.
EB0bankbank 0
If EB is five, bank five is visible.
EB5bankbank 5
Addresses in the fixed area always represent the same RAM cells,
RAM
but these are not additional cells, but the same as banks zero, one and two.
RAMbank 012
This means that there's a total of 8 times 256 words of RAM, two kilowords.
8x256RAM2Ki
ROM is organized similarly. The lower kiloword is banked.
ROM1Kibank
The fixed bank register FB selects one of the 32 banks.
bankFB32bank
Support for more than 32 kilowords of ROM was added at the last minute.
32ROM bank
The 'superbank' bit can switch the uppermost eight banks to the second set.. *laughter*
SUPERBNK8ROM bankbank
so that a total of 40 kilowords are supported by the architecture.
40KiROM
The fixed ROM area will always show the same contents as two of the ROM banks,
ROMROM bank
the designers chose banks two and three to simplify address encoding.
bank 23
In practice, fixed ROM contains core operating system code,
ROM
and fixed RAM core operating system data, that have to be available at all times.
RAM
The remaining functionality is distributed across the different ROM and RAM banks.
ROMRAM bank
Switching the RAM Bank can be done by writing through the EB register.
EBRAM bank
This is not a separate instruction but can be expressed by writing A to memory location three.
A3
If A is five, writing A into EB will make RAM Bank five visible at 3 0 0.
A5AEBRAM bank 5300
The same store instruction could be used to write to the FB register at memory location 4,
4FBROM bank
to switch the ROM Bank. But that wouldn't work for a common case.
If code in one bank wants to call code in another Bank,
bankbank
by first switching the ROM Bank, load FB, and then doing the function call,
FBROM bank
writing the bank number into FB will switch out the bank the code is currently running on,
so it won't be able to execute the call instruction.
call
Instead it will continue running some completely unrelated code
bank
that happens to get the same address on the other bank.
To call code on a different Bank, FB and PC registers need to be changed atomically.
bankFBPC
call f is only a synonym for the existing double word exchange instruction.
call f
Code first has to load the bank and the program counter into A and B.
bankPCAB
Which then call f can atomically move into FB and PC.
call fABFBPC
The same exchange instruction can be used for a far return:
it moves the original values back into FB and PC.
FBPC
The two Bank registers only hold five and three bits respectively.
bank53bank
The other bits are zero and there's a third bank register, BB, both banks,
0BBbank
which merges the information from both other bank registers.
bank
The call far both banks synonym is a double word exchange instruction
bank callfbb
that updates the program counter and both banks.
PCBBRAMROM bank
Subroutines usually have their private variables on particular RAM banks.
RAM bank
Call for both banks passes control to a function on the different ROM Bank
callfbbROM bank
and also directly switches RAM banks, so that the callee can immediately access its variables.
RAM bank
Return for both banks returns to the caller, restoring its RAM Bank configuration.
bank retfbbRAM bank
The unusual ordering of the bank registers was chosen
to allow for a double word exchange of FB and PC,
FBPC
as well as for a double word exchange of PC and BB.
PCBB
Now we've seen all eight registers.
There's eight more special locations in memory above the registers, the shadow area,
which we'll talk about later.
And above those, there are four so-called editing registers,
which make up for the missing shift and rotate instructions.
When writing a 15 bit value into the ROR editing register,
ROR
it will be moved to the right by one bit, and the lowest bit will be cycled to the top.
The result can then be read back.
ROL rotates left,
ROL
SHR shifts to the right duplicating the top bit,
SHR
and SHR7 shifts to the right by 7 bits, filling the top with zeros.
SHR7 70
This is needed for the interpreter system software component that we'll learn about later.
We have seen that the CPU is connected to RAM and ROM over the memory bus,
CPUROMRAM
but computers also talk to peripheral devices that is the I/O bus.
I/O
We've already seen the address space for memory;
there is a second address space to talk to devices.
There are 512 I/O channels numbered 000 through FFF.
512I/O000FFF
Each channel is 15 bits,
and the in and out instructions can read words from -, and write words to I/O channels.
inoutI/O
For many devices, a channel contains 15 individual control bits.
A control bit can for example toggle a lamp on a display.
The 'out OR' instruction sets individual bits,
out|
and 'out AND' clears individual bits.
out&
So I/O instructions can work on the whole word or do boolean operations on them:
I/O
AND, OR and XOR.
To make boolean operations also usable between registers,
channels 1 and 2 are actually aliases of the B and LR registers,
12BLR
which allows for these instructions.
For AND there's also a dedicated instruction that works on A and memory.
A
After the registers, the shadow area, and the editing registers,
there's another special area: the counters.
Like I/O channels, they connect to external devices
I/O
but they don't send bits or hold words back and forth,
instead they are controlled by hardware pulses, or cause hardware pulses.
On every pulse, TIME1 gets incremented for example,
TIME1
while other counters take the number stored into them by code and count down, generating pulses.
When I/O devices need to signal the CPU, thay can interrupt normal execution.
I/OCPU
Next to the program counter, which points to the next instruction,
there's the instruction register which holds the current opcode.
When an interrupt happens, the CPU copies PC into a special memory location PC'
CPUPCPC'
and IR into IR' and then jumps to a magic location depending on the type of interrupt,
IRIR'
in this example 814.
When the interrupt handlers finished servicing the device
the iret instruction will copy PC' and IR' back into PC and IR,
iretPC'IR'PCIR
so execution will continue at the original location.
Memory locations eight through hex F are shadows of the eight registers.
8F8CPU
PC and IR are automatically saved by interrupts
PCIR
and the remaining registers need to be saved by software if necessary.
The overflow condition flag cannot be saved or restored,
so while there's an overflow condition
until the next store instruction, which resolves the overload, interrupts will be disabled.
store
The 11 interrupt handlers have to reside in fixed ROM starting at 8 0 0.
11ROM800
There are 4 words for each entry. Typical interrupt entry code saves A and B,
4AB
loads A and B with a bank and PC of the actual handler and jumps there.
ABbankPCcallfbb
Interrupt 0 is special: it's the entry point on reset.
Next to the interrupt return instruction,
there's an instruction to cause an interrupt in software,
and instructions to enable and disable interrupts globally.
There is one more special memory location at hex 37, the watchdog.
This location needs to be read from or - read from or written to - at least every 0.64 seconds
0.64s
otherwise the hardware will decide the system software is unresponsive and cause a reset.
Now we've seen an instruction set
and in the examples we've seen the codes that represent instructions in memory.
Let's look at how the encoding works.
For the load instruction, the upper three bits are the opcode representing the load a
load3load
and the remaining 12 bits encode the address.
This allows for a total of eight instructions
but there are more than eight instructions.
AGC8
RAM addresses always start with zero zero and ROM adresses start with anything but zero zero.
RAM00ROM
So the store instruction, which only makes sense on RAM,
RAMstore
only needs to encode 10 address bits instead of 12,
making room for another three RAM-only instructions.
23RAM
The same is true for the increment instruction, which makes room for three more,
as well as CCS which shares an opcode with jump, which only works on ROM addresses.
CCSjmpROM00CCS
Since jumps to the bank register don't make much sense
jmpbank
these codes are used to encode STI, CLI and extend.
sticliextend
Extend is a prefix. It changes the meaning of the opcode of the next instruction ...
*laughter* ... allowing for a second set of two-word instructions.
There's one more special call instruction 'call 2' which is 'call LR',
call 2call LR
which is the return instruction.
But the CPU doesn't special case this one.
CPU
Return is a side-effect of calling memory at location 2.
It executes the instruction encoded in the LR register, the 12 bit address
LR
with the leading zeros decodes into another call instruction
30call
which transfers control to the return address.
call
Indexed addressing is achieved by using the index prefix.
index
An indexed instruction consists of two instruction words, index and the base instruction.
The addressing code in the base instruction is the base address
and the index instruction encodes the address of the index.
index
Index is an actual instruction.
extendindex
The CPU reads from the given address, 0 8 0 in the example,
CPUindex080
then adds its value, 3, to the instruction code of the following instruction 3 7 0 0
which is stored in the internal IR register.
IR
Then it uses the resulting instruction code 3 7 0 3 for the next instruction,
CPU3703
which is a load from 703, the effective address.
If an interrupt occurs after in the index instruction, that is no problem
index
because IR contains the effective instruction code which will be saved into IR '
IRIR'
and restored at the end of the interrupt handler.
IR'
Finally there's one index encoding with a special meaning.
index
When the address looks like it's referencing the shadow instruction register
IR'
it's an interrupt return instruction.
Looking at the instruction set architecture as a whole,
AGC
there are many quirky and unusual features when compared to modern architectures.
It uses One's Complement instead of Two's Complement;
it has no status register;
the overflow flag can't even be saved so interrupts are disabled until the overflow is resolved;
the store instruction may skip a word under certain circumstances;
store
the ccs destruction can skip several words and can be outright dangerous
CCS
if the instructions following it use prefixes;
there are no shift or rotate instructions
but magic memory locations that shift and rotate when writing into them;
most boolean instructions only work on I/O channels;
I/O
indexing is done by hacking the following instruction code,
and the architecture has no concept of a stack, indexing has to be used if one is needed.
This was the architecture of the Apollo guidance computer,
now let's look at how this architecture is implemented in hardware.
The hardware implementation runs at one megahertz, is micro coded
1MHz
and uses integrated circuits, core memory, and core rope memory.
We'll look at the block diagram and how instructions are implemented in micro code,
and then about how the schematics map to integrated circuits on modules on trays.
This simplified block diagram shows the AGC at the hardware level.
AGC
Each box contains on the order of 500 logic gates.
The dotted lines are wires that to move a single bit of information,
the solid lines are 15 wires that move a data word.
These units deal with timing and control, and these are the central units.
CPU
The central register unit stores A, B, link registers, and program counter,
ABLRPC
and the arithmetic unit can add and subtract numbers.
The memory components deal with RAM and ROM.
RAMROM
The main clock of about one megahertz feeds into the sequence generator
1MHz
which keeps cycling through twelve stages, which is one memory cycle, MCT.
12MCT
Instructions usually take as many memory cycles as they need memory accesses,
so load, add, and store take two cycles, and jump takes one.
loadaddstore21
The sequence generator contains a collection of 12 step micro programs for each MCT,
for each instruction, like this one for the load instruction.
load1/12
In each step, the entries send control pulses to the other units,
which are connected through the write bus.
The control signal WA for example instructs the register unit to put the contents of A
WAA
onto the write bus, and RA makes it read the value on the bus into A.
RAA
Memory is also connected to the write bus.
WS will copy the bus contents into the memory address register,
WS
and RG and WG will read and write the G register,
RGWGG
which buffers the cells value after read and before a write.
So in stage 7 for example RG puts the memory buffer onto the bus,
loadT7RG
and WB writes the bus contents into the temporary G register.
WBB
CPUBCPUBL
And in T10, B gets put on the bus and it gets read into the A register.
T10A
At the beginning of every memory cycle the hardware sends the memory address S,
usually what's encoded instruction, to memory and copies the contents of that address into G.
G
in the second half of the MCT it stores G back into the same cell.
So if we show memory timing next to the microcode,
as well as the pseudocode version of the load instruction which is easier to read,
we can see it loads the value from memory into G copies it into B
GB
CPUBCPUBL
and then copies it into A.
A
More interesting is the exchange instruction.
It saves A to B, reads memory into G, copies the result into A,
ABGGA
copies the old value into G, and stores that G into memory.
BAGG
Division for example takes several MCT and it's micro program is way more complex.
But there are more micro programs than the ones for the machine instructions.
Since there is only a single adding unit in the whole computer,
incrementing and decrementing the counters is done by converting the pulses into special instructions
that get injected into the instruction stream.
There are 14 of these so-called unprogrammed sequences with their own micro programs.
Some counter shift, some are for interacting with debugging hardware,
and these two control the interrupt and reset sequences.
The complete schematics are publicly available and fit on just 49 sheets.
The whole implementation only uses a single type of gate, a three input NAND gate.
Two of these are contained in one integrated circuit,
and about a hundred of these ICs form a logic module.
24 logic modules and some interface and power supply modules are connected together in tray A,
A24
which also contains the I/O and debug connectors.
I/O
Tray B contains various driver and amplifier modules, as well as RAM and ROM.
BROMRAM
RAM is implemented as magnetic core memory, which stores bits in magnetized toroids.
RAM
Reading a bit clears it, so the memory sequencer makes sure
to always write the value again after reading it.
Without mass storage, like tape, the AGC has an unusually high amount of ROM.
AGCROM
Core Rope Memory encodes bits by wires that either go through- or past a ferrite core.
ROM
The 500,000 bits per computer were woven completely by hand.
50ROM
Trays A and B are put together like this and hermetically sealed,
AB
making for a rather compact computer.
This is its orientation when installed on the spacecraft,
with the six ROM modules accessible so they could in theory be replaced during the mission.
ROM
And that was the hardware part.
*applause* C: Next let's look at the devices.
AGC
*applause*
Let's look at the devices connected to the computer.
AGC
We will look at the core devices that allow the Apollo guidance computer to maintain the state vector,
some quite special devices you don't see on many other computers,
and the peripherals used for communication with astronauts and Mission Control.
The gyroscope is the core peripheral that the Apollo guidance computer was originally built around.
AGC
The Apollo Guidance Computer rotates it into a certain base position with the CDU command counters,
AGCCDU
and then the gyro detects rotation around the three axes of the spacecraft
that can be read from the CDU counters.
CDU
Using the gyroscope, the spacecraft always knows it's attitude, that is its orientation in space.
The accelerometer adjust acceleration forces on the three axis.
The three values can be read from the PIPA counters.
PIPA
The optics on the command module are used to measure the relative position to the celestial bodies.
The computer uses the OPT command counters to move the optics
OPT
to point towards the general direction of a star, and will read in
the astronauts fine-tuning through the OPT counters.
OPT
The landing radar sits at the bottom of the lunar module and
measures the distance to the ground.
The RADARUPT interrupt will be triggered whenever a new measurement is available,
RADARUPT
and the RNRAD counter contains the new value.
RNRAD
Lunar module's rendezvous radar measures the distance of the command and service module during rendezvous.
After setting the two angles and the CDUT and CDUS counters to point it towards the two other spacecraft,
CDUTCDUS
it will automatically track it and cause RADARUPT interrupts when new data is available,
RADARUPT
which can be read from the RNRAD counters.
RNRAD
The command module, the service module, and the lunar module all contain reaction control system,
RCS, jets that emit small bursts for holding or charging the attitude.
RCS
On lunar module, there's one bit for each of the sixteen jets.
Setting a bit to one will make the jet fire.
The system software uses a dedicated timer, TIME6, and it's interrupt T6RUPT for timing the pulses.
TIME6T6RUPTTIME6
The user interface is provided by the so called DSKY
DSKY
which stands for display and keyboard.
DiSplay and KeYboard
It has 19 keys, 15 lamps, and several numeric output lines.
Keys generate the KEYRUPT interrupts and the key number can be read from the KEYIN I/O channel.
KEYRUPTKEYIN I/O
The numeric display is driven by the OUT O channel.
OUTO
There is bidirectional digital radio communication and S-band between Mission Control and each spacecraft
S
at a selectable speed of 1.9 or 51 kbit/s
1.951 kbit/s
Data words from Mission Control show up in the INLINK counter and trigger interrupt UPRUPT.
INLINKUPRUPT
Data words to be sent are stored in the I/O channel DNTM1
I/ODNTM1
and the DOWNRUPT interrupt will signal the program
DOWNRUPT
when it can load the register with the next word.
These were some of the interesting peripherals.
AGC
M: The AGC system, the AGC system software
AGCAGC
makes it a priority based cooperative - but also pre-emptive -
real-time interactive fault tolerant computer with virtual machine support.
JVM
The topics we'll talk about are multitasking, the interpreter, device drivers,
and the waitlist, as well as the user interface, and mechanisms for fault recovery.
The AGC has many things to do.
AGC
It does mathematical calculations that can take several seconds,
and it does I/O with its devices;
I/O
it services interrupts when a device wants the computers attention, for example a key press.
CPU
It does regular servicing of devices, like updating the display,
and it supports real-time control, like flashing a lamp or firing boosters at exactly the right time.
There's only a single CPU, so it must switch between the different tasks.
CPU
Batch processing multitasking computers work on long-running jobs one after the other,
job
but if some jobs have higher priorities
it makes more sense to run a job for only - say 20 milliseconds -
then check the job queues and keep running the highest priority job in the queue
until it terminates and is removed from the queue,
then keep picking the highest priority job.
Jobs have to manually check at least every 20 milliseconds
whether there's a higher priority job in the queue by doing doing a so-called 'yield',
CPUyield
which makes the AGC a priority scheduled cooperative multitasking computer.
AGC
A job is described by 12 word data structure in memory,
that contains the PC and both bank's register
PCbank
that point to where the job will start or continue running,
as well as a word with a disabled flag in the sign bit and a 5 bit priority.
The core set consists of seven job entries.
Core Set7
Minus zero in the priority word means that the entry is empty.
-0
Job zero is always the currently running one.
When a new job gets created with a higher priority,
the yield operation will exchange the 12 words so that new job is job zero.
yield00
Negating the priority will put a job to sleep, so yield won't switch to it again.
Negating it again will wake it up.
The first eight words in the job entry can be used for local storage for the job.
Thread Local Storage, TLS
Since it's always job zero that is running,
these words are always conveniently located at the same addresses in memory.
The executive has a set of subroutines that control the job data structures.
You can create a new job pointed to by a pair of PC and BB registers of a given priority,
PCBB
change the priority of the current job, put the current job to sleep, wake up a given job,
and terminate the current job.
Yield is not an executive function, but a two instruction sequence that checks the new job variable
yieldNEWJOB
in which the executive always holds the idea of the highest priority job.
NEWJOB
If job zero is the highest priority job there's nothing to do.
0CCS
If there is a higher priority job, it calls the change job subroutine which switches to that job.
CCS
NEWJOB isn't just a variable in memory, but also the watchdog word.
NEWJOB
If it isn't accessed regularly, that is cooperative multitasking is stuck,
the hardware will automatically reset itself.
A lot of the code in the AGC does scientific calculations,
AGC
calculating for example just the sum of two products of a scalar and a vector
would require hundreds of instructions in AGC machine code.
AGC
There is library code that provides all kinds of operations
on single, double, or triple precision fixed point values, vectors, and matrices.
It also provides a software multi- purpose accumulator, MPAC,
MPAC
which can hold a double, triple, or a vector, depending on the mode flag.
/
In C-like pseudo code we would load the vector into the MPAC, multiply it with a scalar, save it,
CMPAC
do the other multiplication, and add the result to the saved value.
Formulas like this one need to store intermediate results, so a thirty-eight word stack is provided.
If a job uses math code, the MPAC, the MODE field, and the stack pointer
MPAC
will be stored in the remaining fields of the Core Set Entry.
The stack will be part of a data tructure called VAC,
VAC
VACVector ACcumulator area
which will be pointed to by the Core Set Entry.
VAC
A job can be created with, or without a VAC, depending on which subroutine it is created with.
The machine code version of the example code would still be very verbose,
with many function calls passing pointers.
The designers of the AGC software decided to create a new and compact language
AGC
that will be interpreted at runtime, a virtual machine.
The interpretive language is turing-complete and in addition to the MPAC it has two index registers,
MPAC
two step registers, and its own link register.
The encoding manages to fit two seven bit op codes in one word,
which allows for 128 op codes and explains why there is a 'shift right by seven' function in the CPU.
CPU7
The two operands are stored in the following two words, allowing 14 bit addresses.
14 bit addresses means interpretive code doesn't have to work this complicated memory layout anymore.
14AGC
It allows addressing about half of the ROM at the same time.
ROM
At the lowest kiloword of each half, RAM is visible,
1KiRAM
so interpretive code can pick between one of these two memory layouts.
This is the complete instruction set, regular machine code, interpretive code
can be mixed and matched inside the job.
The exit instruction will continue executing regular machine code at the next address,
EXIT
and CALL INTPRET will similarly switch to interpreter mode.
CALL INTPRET
In addition to long- running math tasks, the system software also supports device drivers.
When a device needs the computers attention, for example in case of a DSKY key press,
CPU
it causes an interrupt.
The current job will be interrupted,
and the interrupt handler will read the device data and return as quickly as possible.
If there's more to do, it can schedule a job for later.
Some devices need to be serviced regularly.
A 120 microsecond timer causes interrupts that read data from and write data to certain devices.
The numeric display of the DSKY for example only allows updating a few digits at a time,
so its driver is triggered by the 120 microsecond timer.
The timer interrupt cycles through eight phases,
which distributes the device drivers across time to minimize the duration of one interrupt handler.
Some devices need to be driven at exact times.
If for example a job decides that it needs to flash a lamp twice,
it would turn it on immediately and schedule three waitlist tasks
in the future at specific times.
The first one will turn the lamp off, the second one will turn it on again
and the third one will turn it off again.
The sorted time deltas of the waitlist tasks are stored in the data structure LST1,
LST1
with the first entry always currently counting down in a timer register,
and LST2 contains a pair of PC and BB for each task.
LST2PCBB
There are subroutines to create a new task and end the current task.
The timer that controls the wait list has a granularity of 10 milliseconds.
Other timers can fire at the same rate, but are offset,
and the work triggered by them is designed to be short enough
to never overlap with the next potential timer triggered work.
This is complicated by device interrupts, which can come in at any time.
The duration of an interrupt handler causes latency
and the maximum duration will reduce the allowed time for the timer handlers.
The core system software makes no guarantees about the timing,
it's all up to components to... it's up to all the components to cooperate
so the real time goal can be met.
The PINBALL program is the shell of the AGC.
PINBALLAGCShell
Key press interrupts schedule a job, that collects the digits for the command
and updates an in-memory representation of what should be on the display.
The 120 millisecond timer triggers the display update code.
When the command is complete PINBALL schedules a new job.
PINBALL
Mission Control has a remote shell in form of a DSKY connected through the s-band radio.
DSKYS
System software that supports human life has to be able to communicate malfunctions
and be able to recover from them.
The alarm subroutine takes the following word from the instruction stream,
ALARM
displays it, and illuminates the prog light.
PROG
This should be interpreted as a warning or an error message.
The AGC software is full of validity and plausibility checks that help to find bugs during development
AGC
bug
and help better understanding potential issues during the mission.
Some kinds of failures triggered by various hardware watchdogs or by code
make it impossible for normal operations to continue.
In addition to showing the error code, they also cause a hardware reset
but the system software also offers recovery services.
A job can have recovery code for its different phases.
During execution it sets the respective phase
and if an abort happens in any job or task, the currently set up recovery routine gets executed
ABORT
which could for example clean up and try the work again, or skip to a different phase,
or cancel the job altogether.
The phase change call sets the current phase for a job in the recovery table,
PHASCHNG
for example phase 5 for job 4.
Each phase is associated with a descriptor of a task or a job with or without a VAC.
VACVAC
So during normal execution with several jobs and tasks scheduled,
if an abort happens, the core set and wait list are cleared,
the contents of the recovery table are activated,
scheduling tasks and jobs for all jobs that set up recovery code.
Sometimes a failure though, like corrupted memory, are not recoverable.
They cause a fresh start, meaning a full initialization of the system without running any recovery code.
And that was the AGC system software.
AGC
C: As we now have a good overview on architecture, hardware, peripherals, and system software
of the Apollo Guidance Computer, it's time briefly view on it's practical use on a mission to the moon.
We will look at the user interface, the launch sequence, and, once in orbit, the attitude in orbit determination.
Further we will understand how the digital autopilot works,
and how powered flight is being performed.
As soon as we've reached the moon, we look at the lunar landing and the lunar rendezvous after liftoff
and finally re-entry into Earth's atmosphere.
Last but not least contingencies, or as we like to call them, "fun issues".
Let's start with the user interface.
It is like any command-line interface but since there are only numbers and no letters,
key words have to be encoded.
On a normal system you might say 'display memory', 'enter'.
Enter
Display is the verb, memory is the noun.
On the Apollo guidance computer you say verb '0 1', which means 'display',
AGC01
noun '0 2' - 'memory' - 'enter'.
02Enter
Subroutine asks for an argument.
On a normal system it might display a prompt, you enter the number, press 'enter'.
Enter
On the Apollo Guidance Computer, flashing 'verb' and 'noun' indicate that is waiting for input.
AGC
So you type '2 5', 'enter'; an octal address, and the Apollo Guidance Computer displays the result.
25EnterAGC
AGC1512
The memory contents at the address octal '2 5'.
The Apollo Guidance Computer uses the same concept of verb and noun when it proactively asks for input.
AGC
Verb '6', noun '11' asks for the CSI ignition time.
611AGCCSI
CSI meaning Coelliptic Sequence Initiation, we will come to that later.
CSI
Special case is when the Apollo Guidance Computer asks a yes-or-no question.
AGC
Verb 99 has the astronaut confirm engine ignition with a proceed key.
99PROProceed
The astronauts have a complete reference of all verbs and nouns on paper,
as well as cue cards were the most important information.
Let's now go through each of the phases of the mission, starting with a liftoff.
So, we are on our way. The Apollo Guidance Computer is in passive monitoring mode.
AGC
With the cutting of the umbilical cables, which you see right about ... now,
it has started the mission clock.
In case this trigger fails, one DSKY is always prepared with verb 75 and just waiting for 'enter'
DSKY75Enter
to manually start the mission timer.
We can display the mission elapsed time at any time with verb 16, noun 65.
During the flight with the SaturnV, the Apollo Guidance Computer is only performing passive monitoring of the flight.
AGC
Control of the SaturnV is with its own launch vehicle digital computer, and the instrument unit ring.
The DSKY automatically shows verb 16, noun 62, which is velocity in feet per second.
DSKY1662/
Altitude change rate in feet per second, and altitude above pad and nautical miles.
/
Note that the units and the position of the decimal point are implicit,
and yes the whole system was working in metric internally
but for the benefit of the American astronauts the display procedures converted everything to imperial units.
*laughter and applause*
In case of problems with the Saturn computer,
the Apollo Guidance Computer can take over full control of the launch vehicle,
in extreme cases astronauts could even steer the whole stack into orbit themselves with the hand controller.
In case you ever wanted to fly... to manually control a 110 meter tall rocket
1103000
with more than 30 million Newton of thrust, this is your chance.
*laughter* In less than 12 minutes we've gone through
the first and second stage and are using a small burn from the third stage
to get us into a 185 kilometer orbit which circles the earth every 88 minutes.
But how do we know where ... we are in the right orbit?
Well the Apollo guidance computer, as well as Mission Control, are monitoring position and velocity,
AGC
because to get where we want to be, we first need to know where we are.
To be able to navigate in space, we need to maintain our three-dimensional position,
and our three-dimensional velocity, the so-called state vector.
Let's start with the determination of the position.
For this we need a telescope and a space sextant.
The space sextant is very similar to an 18th century nautical sextant.
Position is determined by measuring the angle between the horizon and a celestial body.
As an horizon we can either take that of Earth or Moon
and celestial bodies - well we are in orbit, we are surrounded by them. So let's just pick one.
Luckily the Apollo guidance computer already knows the position of 45 of them.
AGC45
The whole optics hardware and the command and service module can be moved
to point in the general direction of Earth and moon.
With the launch of program 52, we command the Apollo guidance computer to rotate the spacecraft
P52AGC
to point one axis of the sextant, the so-called landmark line- of-sight, LLOS, to the nearest body,
LLOS
which is earth or moon.
The astronaut then used the optics systems to exactly align the horizon to the LLOS.
With the telescope the astronaut looks for one of the known stars,
points the star line to it and lets the Apollo guidance computer read the trunnion and shaft angle.
AGC
Repeating this one or more times in a different plane gives a three-dimensional position of the vehicle in space.
In the lunar module on the other hand, the optics hardware was trimmed down for weight reduction.
Any alignment requires rotation of the lunar module.
This is mostly used to determine the landing site and support the rendezvous maneuvre.
It even lacks the software to perform positioning in translunar space.
As we are moving, our position changes all the time.
But after 2 location fixes, as long as we're coasting,
we are able to establish our speed and can determine future positions by dead reckoning.
As position and velocity are known, future positions can be extrapolated.
Unfortunately the near extrapolation doesn't work in space
as we have gravitational forces which bend our path.
Thankfully there are two mathematical models implemented in the Apollo Guidance Computer:
AGC
Conic integration based on the Keplerian orbit model on the left,
which assumes one perfectly round gravitational body influencing our flight path,
and Encke's integrating method for perturbation considering multiple bodies with gravitational imbalances.
Encke
I think this helps to understand why we need a computer on board
and can't just fly to the moon with a hand controller.
As we see, the Apollo spacecraft was perfectly capable to fly on its own,
but in the end NASA decided that the primary source for state vector updates
NASA
shall be Mission Control in Houston, measured with three ground stations.
Remote programming is done with the Apollo guidance Computer in idle, and running program 27.
AGCP27
Mission Control can use its link via s-band to update the state vector.
S
But there's one thing Mission Control doesn't know better than us, and that's attitude.
Attitude is the orientation of the spacecraft in its three axis.
Starting from a known attitude, we have to ensure that we can measure any rotation on any axis.
That's what gyros are for.
They are one of the major component of the IMU, the inertial measurement unit.
IMU
Three gyroscopes, one per axis measure any rotation and provide their data to the Apollo Guidance Computer
AGC
to keep track of the attitude of the spacecraft.
Before we leave Earth orbit, let's quickly discuss the digital autopilot.
It is the single biggest program in the Apollo Guidance Computer,
AGC
with about 10% of all the source code both in the command and service module as well as the lunar module.
10%
The implementations for each vehicle are significantly different though,
due to different flight modes, thruster sets, and symmetry of vehicle.
As there's no friction in space, the tiniest event would constantly make the spacecraft rotate.
The digital autopilot of the Apollo Guidance Computer uses the jets
AGCRCS
to maintain the attitude within certain thresholds, so-called dead bands.
The autopilot is also used in case the astronauts ever need to use the hand controllers for thrusters.
Basically both the command service module and the lunar module have fly-by-wire control.
As any thruster could break at any time, the autopilot is capable of calculating
the ideal burn mode even with a reduced number of thrusters.
It has some simple algorithms for center of gravity and weight distribution as well,
AGC
which are taken into account when calculating thruster maneuvers.
It can do more than that, though.
Give it a new attitude and it will calculate the most efficient transfer vector to reach the new attitude.
In certain flight modes it might be required to have a stable rotation,
be it for temperature control, monitoring of the landing site, or other reasons.
The autopilot supports stable constant rolling, which can be directly activated.
The autopilot does not only control attitude, it also supports the crew in performing powered flight maneuvers.
It calculates a potential solution, which obviously can be overwritten by ground as usual,
but still, after confirmation the autopilot automatically fires the engines
and keeps a timer for the correct length of time.
It does not measure the results of the burn though.
For powered flight obviously dead reckoning isn't correct anymore,
so the Apollo Guidance Computer contains a subroutine called average G,
AGCGAverage G
which takes the input from the IMU, meaning gyro and accelerometer,
IMU
to compute the change to the state vector.
Now that we know how to orient ourselves, and how to control the spaceship,
it's time we fly to the moon.
Usually the translunar injection happens in the middle of the second orbit around the earth,
so around 2 hours 45 minutes into the flight.
This is still performed by the third stage of the SaturnV
so the Apollo Guidance Computer once again should only have a passive role here
AGC
by monitoring the translunar injection with the dedicated program P 15.
P15
After separation from the S-IV-B we are on our way.
Since the next interesting phase is the lunar landing, let's skip to that one.
Once in lunar orbit, separation between the command and service module and lunar module
happens four hours and 45 minutes before landing.
On the lunar module, directly afterwards, rendezvous equipment like radar, strobe and VHF are tested,
as well as the IMU, which is realigned.
IMU
Additionally there's lots of preparation work on the lunar module.
One of the main tasks is to prepare the abort guidance system, AGS,
AGS
which is another, more simpler computer,
that is able to get the lunar module with the astronauts back into orbit
and safely docked with the CSM in case of an emergency.
Let's get back to powered descent.
The lunar module AGC has a special program for that one, P 63, braking phase.
AGCP63
The landing radar has switched on and updates the state vector.
The Apollo Guidance Computer controls the burn to reach the correct corridor towards the surface
AGC
with a minimal amount of fuel.
This is fully automatic, the astronauts just sit along for the ride.
The lunar module is oriented with its descent engine towards the moon, visibility for the astronauts is close to zero.
The second program, P 64, starts automatically at around 8,000 feet.
P648000
8000=2438.4
Lunar module is pitched so that the astronauts can actually see the ground
and the lunar module commander is getting a better understanding of the landing site and can search for a suitable spot.
The third program, P 68, keeps the lunar module in a stable attitude above the surface
P66
and the commander manually adjusts the height in one feet per second increments,
to slowly descend to the surface.
Ideally at that point, the horizontal movement of the lunar module should be zero.
After touchdown the crew manually activates program 68,
P68
which confirms to the Apollo guidance computer that yes, we have indeed landed,
AGC
and ensures that the engine is switched off, terminates the average G routine,
G
and sets the autopilot in a very forgiving setting,
to avoid any corrections when it measures the rotation of the moon.
The autopilot is not completely switched off though,
as the astronaut might need it in case of an emergency ascent.
Well we are on the moon, we do the usual stuff,
small step for man, jump around plant the flag, and we then skip directly to the interesting bits
which is liftoff and rendezvous.
The rendezvous technique was developed in the Gemini project.
Here you can see the Agena rendezvous target in Earth orbit.
It follows the principle of an active vehicle, in this case the lunar module,
which follows the command and service module and approaches it from below at slightly faster orbit.
There were actually two different ways for rendezvous.
A more conservative method called Coelliptic rendezvous
which required one and a half orbits for the lunar module to reach the command and service module,
but gave ample opportunity for monitoring progress, mid- course corrections, and orbit scenarios.
And a more risky direct rendezvous method
which directly aimed the lunar module towards the command and service module,
taking less than one orbit until docking.
This one was used starting from the Apollo 14 mission,
as Mission Control had more experience and aimed for the shorter, less fuel intensive method.
Preparation had to start two hours before liftoff.
We have to align the IMU and we visually monitor the orbit of the CSM and calculate the rendezvous data.
IMU
The Apollo Guidance Computer has program 22, CSM tracking, for this purpose.
AGCP22
At liftoff minus one hour, we start program 12, powered ascent,
P12
and feed it with the necessary data, liftoff time and velocity target.
The Apollo Guidance Computer performs the countdown, and ask for confirmation,
AGC
we proceed and we have liftoff.
The trip into orbit takes only seven and a half minutes
but depending on which method for reaching the target orbit was used,
it takes us either one and a half, or three and a half hours to come up behind the command and service module.
During that time, program 20 is running all the time, measuring the state vector of the other vehicle,
P20
the command and service module, via various peripherals like rendezvous radar,
VHF antenna, and the optic system for visual alignment.
It calculates the necessary corridor and respective maneuvers required
to get the lunar module into an interception course.
Multiple other programs run in parallel to perform the necessary mid-course burn maneuvers.
On the commander of service module, the pilot is actively tracking the lunar module the whole way up to orbit.
The command and service module's computer is calculating the state vector of the lunar module,
to take over the role of the active vehicle, in case anything goes wrong.
The approach of the lunar module stops at 50 meter distance,
at which point it rotates to point its docking target on top towards the command and service module.
At that point in time the command service module takes over the active role
and activates program 79, final rendezvous,
P79
which slows down the command and service module to close the distance until docking.
Seconds before contact, the autopilot on both spacecraft is switched off
to avoid both trying to correct the attitude of the combined spacecraft.
So far so good, time to go home with the trans-earth injection.
We feed the Apollo guidance computer with Earth orbit parameters
AGC
and let it calculate the burn which is then activated and controlled.
Any kind of potential mid-course corrections are performed the exact same way.
Once in orbit around Earth, re-entry parameters are calculated on ground
and transferred to the Apollo guidance computer via a S-band uplink.
SAGC
The first entry program, P 61, entry preparation, starts at entry minus 25 minutes.
P6125
Various landing parameters are requested, like latitude and longitude of the splash zone,
as well as the velocity and angles to enter the atmosphere.
Entering and confirming these values completes program 61, and starts program 62,
P61P62
which basically asks the astronaut to perform a checklist
for manual command module - service module - separation,
which is not controlled by the Apollo guidance computer.
AGC
After that has been performed it switches automatically to program 63, entry initialization.
P63
At that point, the autopilot is taking care of thruster control
to break the command module out of its orbit into Earth's atmosphere.
The main program for re-entry is program 64, entry, which starts automatically.
P64
Program 64 monitors the trajectory, and splashdown location,
and determines the best entry solution and potential velocity reduction by invoking two specific programs,
either P 65, entry up control, which basically makes the command module surf on the atmosphere
P65
to reduce speed and extend the range,
or program 66, entry ballistic, throwing us through the atmosphere like a cannonball.
P66
The right mixture of the two is decided by program 64.
P64
The last program, program 67, final phase, performs the final maneuvers to the splash down.
P67
The following steps, like parachute deployment and so on, are not done by the Apollo guidance computer
AGC
but by the ELSC, the Earth Landing Sequence Controller.
ELSC
The job of the Apollo guidance computer is done before deploying the parachutes.
So this was a beautiful nominal mission, what can go wrong?
Well let's start with Apollo 11, which had a 12 02 program alarm during powered descent.
Normally programs during powered descent use about 85% of the processing power of the computer,
85%
but due to an incorrect power supply design,
the rendezvous radar generated an additional twelve thousand eight hundred involuntary instructions per seconds,
ironically amounting to the exact additional 15 percent load.
15%
Due to the co-operative multitasking, a queue of jobs build up,
which resulted in executive overflow and the 12 02 alarm.
The operating system automatically performed a program abort, all jobs were cancelled and restarted.
All of this took just a few seconds, and landing could commence.
Next, Apollo 13. They had an explosion of the oxygen tank in the service module at 55 hours 54 minutes 53 seconds
13555453
and it will ... yep, correct, 320,000 kilometers from Earth.
Fortunately they could make use of the free return trajectory to get the astronauts back to earth
but they had to move to the lunar module to survive, as the command and service module was completely shut down,
including its Apollo Guidance Computer.
The IMU settings needed to be transferred to the lunar module system first,
IMU
adapted to the different orientations of the spacecraft.
The manual burns and the mid-course corrections were actually done with the abort guidance system on the lunar module,
due to power constraints with the Apollo Guidance Computer.
AGC
Successful reboot of the command and service module computer was luckily done hours before re- entry.
And last but not least, Apollo 14, which had a floating solder ball in the abort button,
which might lead to an unwanted activation of abort, therefore putting the lunar module back into orbit.
This was solved within hours, by reprogramming the Apollo Guidance Computer,
AGC
to spoof the execution of a different program, which was not listening to the abort button during the powered descend.
Real abort activation though would have to be manually activated via the DSKY.
DSKY
So this was an overview and how the mission software was used on a flight to the moon and back.
*applause*
M: Now you probably want to run your own code on a real Apollo Guidance Computer,
so you need to know where to find one.
42 computers were built total. Seven lunar module computers crashed onto the moon.
Three lunar module AGC's burned up in the Earth's atmosphere,
11 command module computers returned.
They're all presumably parts of museum exhibits.
And 21 machines were not flown. Little is known about those.
One is on display at the Computer History Museum in Mountain View, California, but it is missing some components.
Luckily several emulation solutions are publicly available, as well as a tool chain.
And the complete mission source, originally the size of a medium-sized suitcase, is available on github. *laughter*
GitHub
*applause*
It takes a village to create a presentation.
We would like to thank everyone who helped and supported us.
This includes the indirect contributors, who wrote the books,
the original documentation, the websites, and the software.
Thank you very much for your attention. C: Thank you.
*applause and cheering*
Herald: Wow that was a densely packed talk. *laughter*
Thanks Michael, and thanks Christian, for this amazing information overload.
MichaelChristian
Please give a warm hand of applause, because we can't have a Q&A, unfortunately.
*applause*
*postroll music*
c3subtitles.de
RigoLigo
*subtitles created by c3subtitles.de in the year 2018*
https://github.com/RigoLigoRLC/rigo-open-subtitles
CC-0